Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we're talking about an uncomfortable subject, not because
我是Catherine，今天我们聊一个不太舒服的话题，不是因为
it's uncomfortable to talk about, but because it's, well, it doesn't really feel good when
聊起来不舒服，而是因为，嗯，当你不得不去做的时候，
you have to go do it.
感觉确实不太好。
That's right.
没错。
Today we're going to the doctor, but because we need to get vaccines.
今天我们要去看医生，但因为我们得打疫苗。
All right.
好的。
So vaccines, these are, well, let's listen out during the dialogue and maybe you can
所以，疫苗，这些是，嗯，我们先听听对话，也许你能
guess what this word means when we come back, we'll be defining it for you, talking about
猜出这个词的意思，等我们回来会为你解释，讨论
different kinds of vaccines, but just remember that we're talking about going to the doctor
不同类型的疫苗，但请记住，我们说的是去看医生
to get these shots.
打这些针。
So let's take a listen to that dialogue.
那我们就来听听这段对话吧。
Hello Mrs. Parker.
你好，帕克太太。
How have you been?
你最近怎么样？
Hello, Dr. Peters.
你好，彼得斯医生。
Just fine.
挺好的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Ricky and I are here for his vaccines.
我和里基是来打疫苗的。
Very well.
好的。
Let's see.
让我看看。
According to the vaccination record, Ricky has received his polio, tetanus and hepatitis
根据疫苗接种记录，里基已经打过脊髓灰质炎、破伤风和乙肝
B shots.
疫苗。
He is 14 months old, so he is due for hepatitis A, chicken pox and measles shots.
他现在14个月大，所以该打甲肝、水痘和麻疹疫苗了。
What about rubella and mumps?
那风疹和腮腺炎呢？
Well, I can only give him these for now and after a couple of weeks I can administer the
嗯，我现在只能给他打这些，过几周后我可以再给他打
rest.
剩下的。
Okay, great.
好的，太好了。
Doctor, I think I also may need a tetanus booster.
医生，我想我可能也需要打一针破伤风加强针。
Last time I got it was maybe 15 years ago.
上次打大概是15年前了。
We'll check our records and I'll have the nurse administer the booster as well.
我们会查一下记录，然后让护士也给你打加强针。
Now please hold Ricky's arm tight.
现在请抓紧里基的胳膊。
This may sting a little.
可能会有点刺痛。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now let's take a look at all of these words that are a little bit difficult, but we'll
现在让我们看看这些有点难的词，我们会在“语言小贴士”环节
try to define them on Language Takeaway.
试着解释它们。
Language Takeaway.
语言小贴士。
So Marco, first off, what is a vaccine?
那么Marco，首先，什么是疫苗？
So a vaccine we can say is a type of medicine.
疫苗可以说是一种药物。
But it's basically an injection or medicine where you're helping a person defend him or
但它基本上是一种注射或药物，帮助一个人防御
herself against a specific type of disease.
某种特定的疾病。
Okay, so vaccination is medicine you receive before you're sick so that in the future you
好的，所以疫苗是在你生病前接种的药物，这样将来
won't get sick with that disease.
你就不会得那种病了。
That's right.
没错。
So that's a vaccine.
这就是疫苗。
There are many, many different types of vaccines.
有很多很多不同类型的疫苗。
And of course, when you do get them, you need to keep track of them via a vaccination record.
当然，当你接种时，你需要通过疫苗接种记录来跟踪。
So a record is basically a list or a document that shows what has been done.
所以记录基本上是一份清单或文件，显示已经做了什么。
And this is very important when you go to the doctor to have a record of the things
当你去看医生时，有记录非常重要，记录你
that you have received, the vaccines you've received.
已经接种过的疫苗。
So for example, if I have a baby and I want the baby to have vaccinations, we'd have to
比如，如果我有孩子，我想让孩子接种疫苗，我们就得
keep a record of all of his vaccinations.
记录他所有的疫苗接种情况。
That's right.
没错。
So we are, obviously we get different vaccines at different stages in our life.
显然，我们在人生的不同阶段会接种不同的疫苗。
Let's talk about some of the ones that we're taking a look at today.
我们来聊聊今天看到的一些疫苗。
So for example, we have a tetanus vaccine or a tetanus shot.
比如，我们有破伤风疫苗或破伤风针。
All right, the tetanus shot is very famous because it's maybe the most painful.
好的，破伤风针很有名，因为它可能是最疼的。
It really makes you sore for a little while.
它真的会让你疼一阵子。
And most people get the tetanus shot when they're very young.
大多数人很小的时候就打了破伤风针。
This prevents you from getting the disease tetanus.
这能防止你得破伤风这种病。
And tetanus is something you can get from animals or from dirty nails, dirty metal,
破伤风可能从动物或脏钉子、脏金属，
anything that pokes out at you.
任何刺伤你的东西那里感染。
And so you get the tetanus shot, but then after your tetanus shot, every five or 10
所以你打了破伤风针，但之后每五到十年，
years, you need to get a booster shot.
你需要打一针加强针。
So there's the tetanus shot and there's the tetanus booster.
所以有破伤风针和破伤风加强针。
So when we talk about a booster, when we're talking about vaccines, is basically you are
当我们谈到加强针，在疫苗的语境下，基本上就是
reinforcing it.
强化它。
You are making it stronger because obviously over time it becomes weak.
你让它更强效，因为显然随着时间的推移它会变弱。
The medicine won't last forever.
药物不会永远有效。
So you need to get a booster to make sure that you are still protected.
所以你需要打加强针来确保你仍然受到保护。
Basically it's an update.
基本上就是一次更新。
That's right.
没错。
So we have tetanus and tetanus booster, but we have another kind of vaccine.
所以我们有破伤风和破伤风加强针，但还有另一种疫苗。
The disease here is called hepatitis.
这种病叫肝炎。
That's right.
没错。
So we're taking a look at hepatitis B and hepatitis A. So there are different types
我们来看看乙肝和甲肝。所以有不同类型的
of hepatitis.
肝炎。
That's right.
没错。
So both kinds of hepatitis you can catch from other people.
两种肝炎都可以从别人那里传染。
Although hepatitis A, I believe you can catch from saliva or contact.
虽然甲肝，我认为可以通过唾液或接触传染。
Whereas hepatitis B you catch from other people's blood or if you have a relationship with
而乙肝是通过他人的血液或与某人发生关系而感染的。
someone.
某人。
So hepatitis A and B are different.
所以甲肝和乙肝是不同的。
Hepatitis B affects your liver and so there's different kinds of severity here.
乙肝会影响你的肝脏，而且严重程度各有不同。
Now hepatitis A and B there are vaccinations for.
现在甲肝和乙肝都有疫苗可以接种。
You can get those shots and it's very important if you're traveling to places that require
你可以打这些针，如果你要去需要这些疫苗的地方旅行，这非常重要，
them so that you don't get sick.
这样你就不会生病。
Okay.
好的。
So, well, these different types of hepatitis, they are dangerous, right?
那么，这些不同类型的肝炎都很危险，对吧？
And they could be fatal.
而且它们可能是致命的。
But another one that's very, very common, especially with young kids, we have chicken
但另一种非常非常常见的，尤其是对小孩子来说，就是水痘。
pox.
水痘。
Chicken pox.
Now it's kind of a funny name, chicken pox, P-O-X.
这个名字挺有趣的，水痘，拼写是P-O-X。
But it's also like you say, very common.
但就像你说的，它也非常常见。
So basically the symptoms are what?
那么基本上症状是什么？
You get these red bumps all over your body and they itch.
你全身会长出这些红色的小疙瘩，而且很痒。
You want to scratch and scratch and scratch.
你会想不停地抓、抓、抓。
And so I remember when I had this, I was a little kid.
我记得我小时候得过这个。
My mom said, don't scratch because if you scratch, it will leave a mark.
我妈妈说，别抓，因为如果你抓了，会留下印记。
Right.
对。
It leaves a scar.
会留下疤痕。
So yeah, chicken pox, you get these little rashes all over your body.
所以是的，水痘，你全身会长出这些小皮疹。
They're very itchy, but they will go away with time.
它们非常痒，但过一段时间就会消退。
Now it's usually, I've heard that it's recommended that people get it.
我听说通常建议人们得一次水痘。
Actually you should get it when you're young because it's more dangerous if you get it
实际上你应该在年轻时得，因为如果成年后得会更危险。
as an adult.
作为成年人。
That's right.
没错。
It's very painful as an adult.
成年后得水痘会很痛苦。
So basically chicken pox, they say if you get it once, you can't get it again.
所以基本上水痘，他们说如果你得了一次，就不会再得了。
You'll never get it again.
你永远不会再得。
So if you get it as an adult, it's shingles, it's very painful.
所以如果你成年后得，那就是带状疱疹，非常痛苦。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
So we've taken a look at a lot of vocab here.
我们已经看了很多词汇。
Why don't we now jump to another section.
我们现在为什么不跳到另一个部分呢？
Let's continue talking about these different types of vaccines.
让我们继续讨论这些不同类型的疫苗。
Let's go to language takeaway part two.
让我们进入语言要点第二部分。
All right.
好的。
So we have this special category of vaccinations.
所以我们有这一特殊类别的疫苗接种。
They usually go together.
它们通常一起进行。
We have mumps, measles, and rubella, or there's a special acronym, MMR, mumps, measles, rubella.
我们有腮腺炎、麻疹和风疹，或者有一个特殊的缩写，MMR，腮腺炎、麻疹、风疹。
Okay.
好的。
So you basically get like a little combo.
所以你基本上会得到一个小组合。
You usually get all three of them at one go.
你通常一次性接种这三种。
So what are these measles?
那么麻疹是什么？
All right.
好的。
Measles.
麻疹。
Well, measles is a virus.
嗯，麻疹是一种病毒。
He's got the measles.
他得了麻疹。
You often read books from like the 19th century where everyone gets the measles when they're
你经常读到19世纪的书，里面每个人小时候都得麻疹。
a child.
小时候。
But measles is basically a virus, but it's kind of like the chicken pox because you get
但麻疹基本上是一种病毒，有点像水痘，因为你皮肤上会出现皮疹。
a rash on your skin.
你的皮肤上。
And is it fatal?
它会致命吗？
Can you die from the measles?
你会死于麻疹吗？
I think in the old days you could, but these days it's pretty, pretty easy to take care
我想在过去可能会，但现在处理起来相当容易。
of.
处理。
And what about mumps?
那腮腺炎呢？
Now mumps, I'm not too sure about this, but I've heard that mumps is like a swelling in
腮腺炎，我不太确定，但我听说腮腺炎是下巴和耳朵之间的部位肿胀。
the space between your jaw and your ear.
下巴和耳朵之间的部位。
So you know where your ear kind of comes down to your jaw.
所以你知道耳朵向下延伸到下巴的地方。
That part of your head starts to swell and is very uncomfortable.
你头部的那个部位开始肿胀，非常不舒服。
Right.
对。
And it could cause, like the consequences could be fatal, right?
而且它可能导致，后果可能是致命的，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
So what about rubella?
那风疹呢？
Rubella is another kind of rash.
风疹是另一种皮疹。
And from my reading, I saw that rubella is not very dangerous for most people, but it
根据我的阅读，我发现风疹对大多数人来说并不危险，但对孕妇非常危险。
is very dangerous for pregnant women.
对孕妇非常危险。
So most pregnant women are tested for rubella or the rubella vaccine, and they're told to
所以大多数孕妇会接受风疹或风疹疫苗的检测，并被告知在怀孕前接种疫苗，
get the vaccine before they're pregnant so that they don't get this disease and harm
这样她们就不会得这种病并伤害到宝宝，
their baby because they can have a miscarriage if they get rubella while they're pregnant.
因为如果她们在怀孕期间得了风疹，可能会导致流产。
Right, right.
对，对。
Okay, so pretty much you want to get all these vaccines to make sure that you don't get sick
好的，所以基本上你想接种所有这些疫苗，以确保你将来不会生病。
in the future.
将来不会生病。
Now, when we were talking about getting the vaccines, the doctor said, he didn't say you're
现在，当我们谈论接种疫苗时，医生没有说“你将接种疫苗”或“我会给你打疫苗”。
going to get the vaccines or I'm going to give you a vaccine.
接种疫苗。
He said, I'll have the nurse administer the vaccine or administer the booster.
他说：“我会让护士来接种疫苗或接种加强针。”
That's right.
没错。
So the verb here that we use with vaccine is to administer.
所以我们和疫苗一起使用的动词是“接种”。
And this is something that the nurse does or the doctor does.
这是护士或医生做的事情。
And it's just a way to say that the nurse will give you this shot, to give you a shot.
这只是一种说法，意思是护士会给你打针，给你打一针。
But administer is more formal.
但“administer”这个词更正式。
It's more common in the medical kind of medical talk.
它在医学类的对话中更常见。
So you'd say administer the test or administer the vaccine.
所以你会说“administer the test”或“administer the vaccine”。
So for example, a doctor would say, I'm going to administer a shot of penicillin.
比如，医生会说，我要给你打一针青霉素。
That's right.
没错。
Or I'm going to administer this blood test.
或者我要给你做这个血检。
That means I'm actually going to do it right now.
意思是我现在就要做这件事。
Now, obviously these vaccines, some of them you can take as a little pill.
现在，显然这些疫苗，有些可以吃小药片。
Some of them you can take as drops, like, you know, it's very painless, but some of
有些可以滴剂服用，比如，你知道的，非常无痛，但有些
them you have to get a shot and sometimes they do hurt.
必须打针，有时确实会疼。
And we saw in the dialogue that the doctor said, this may sting a little.
我们在对话中看到，医生说，这可能会有点刺痛。
Doctors always say this before they give you a shot.
医生在打针前总是这么说。
This may sting a little.
这可能会有点刺痛。
Now sting is a verb that means to hurt, but it's not like I hit you in the face, boom,
现在，“sting”是一个动词，意思是疼，但不像我打你脸，砰，
it stings.
刺痛。
No, a sting is like a kind of a very kind of light hurt.
不，刺痛是一种很轻微的疼痛。
It's like a pinch.
就像捏一下。
It's like a small, sharp pain, small, sharp pain.
就像一种小而尖锐的疼痛，小而尖锐的疼痛。
That's a good way to describe it.
这是个很好的描述方式。
So oftentimes we talk about bees, you know, bees that fly around, they sting you.
所以我们经常说蜜蜂，你知道，飞来飞去的蜜蜂，它们会蜇你。
Right.
对。
So it's a small, sharp pain.
所以它是一种小而尖锐的疼痛。
Right.
对。
Okay.
好的。
Very good.
很好。
So let's listen to the dialogue again.
那么让我们再听一遍对话。
Let's keep a lookout for how we pronounce all of these words and we'll be back in a
让我们留意一下这些单词的发音，我们一会儿
bit.
回来。
Hello, Mrs. Parker.
你好，帕克太太。
How have you been?
你最近怎么样？
Hello, Dr. Peters.
你好，彼得斯医生。
Just fine, thank you.
我很好，谢谢。
Ricky and I are here for his vaccines.
我和瑞奇来这里打疫苗。
Very well.
很好。
Let's see.
让我看看。
According to his vaccination record, Ricky has received his polio, tetanus and hepatitis
根据他的疫苗接种记录，瑞奇已经接种了小儿麻痹症、破伤风和乙肝
B shots.
疫苗。
He is 14 months old, so he is due for hepatitis A, chicken pox and measles shots.
他14个月大，所以该打甲肝、水痘和麻疹疫苗了。
What about rubella and mumps?
那风疹和腮腺炎呢？
Well, I can only give him these for now and after a couple of weeks I can administer the
嗯，我现在只能给他打这些，几周后我可以给他接种
rest.
剩下的。
Okay, great.
好的，太好了。
Doctor, I think I also may need a tetanus booster.
医生，我想我可能也需要打一针破伤风加强针。
Last time I got it was maybe 15 years ago.
上次打大概是15年前了。
We'll check our records and I'll have the nurse administer the booster as well.
我们会查一下记录，然后让护士也给你打加强针。
Now please hold Ricky's arm tight.
现在请抓紧瑞奇的手臂。
This may sting a little.
这可能会有点刺痛。
So nowadays, most of these shots are administered when the babies are just born.
所以现在，大多数这些疫苗都是在婴儿刚出生时接种的。
They're still in the hospital and they get a lot of vaccines to prevent them from getting
他们还在医院里，就会接种很多疫苗来预防
these things.
这些疾病。
That's right.
没错。
I remember when I was a kid, we didn't even have a vaccine for chicken pox.
我记得我小时候，我们甚至没有水痘疫苗。
So these days there are more and more.
所以现在疫苗越来越多了。
The oldest I think is the polio vaccine, the one that we hear the most about because it
最古老的我认为是小儿麻痹症疫苗，我们听到最多的也是它，因为
was a very serious disease that affected a lot of people up until the 1940s and 50s,
它是一种非常严重的疾病，直到20世纪40年代和50年代还影响了很多
I believe.
人，我想。
So yeah, it's important really to read about these things and to educate yourself so that
所以，是的，了解这些事情并自我教育真的很重要，这样
you know what you should get yourself and your kids.
你才知道自己和孩子们应该接种什么。
That's exactly right because it's very important.
完全正确，因为这非常重要。
Most of these diseases or most of these viruses have been eradicated because more and more
大多数这些疾病或大多数这些病毒已经被根除，因为越来越
people have had access to vaccines.
多的人能够接种疫苗。
Like for example, polio, it's very rare you would say to actually get it nowadays because
比如小儿麻痹症，现在你很少会真的得这种病，因为
there's a vaccine, but it's very, very important I think.
有疫苗，但我认为这非常重要。
But some people get a little bit too nervous.
但有些人会有点过于紧张。
Like for example, whenever they travel to a tropical country, they're always afraid
比如，每当他们去热带国家旅行时，总是害怕
of yellow fever, so they get yellow fever shots.
黄热病，所以他们会打黄热病疫苗。
But I've never really seen anyone get yellow fever because you go to like Thailand for
但我从没见过有人得黄热病，因为你去泰国之类的地方
a week.
只待一周。
A friend of mine went to Thailand and got dengue fever.
我一个朋友去了泰国，得了登革热。
So there's no vaccination for this, but it is a very painful disease you can get in tropical
所以没有疫苗可以预防这个，但这是在热带地区可能得的一种
places.
很痛苦的疾病。
So I think the moral is talk to your doctor, see what he or she suggests because they will
所以我认为重点是，和你的医生谈谈，看看他或她建议什么，因为他们
understand maybe better than you will.
可能比你更了解。
And then just follow their advice for different places that you're traveling to.
然后根据你去不同地方旅行的情况，听从他们的建议。
That's right.
没错。
So that's all the time we have for today, but if you guys have any questions or doubts,
这就是我们今天的所有内容，但如果你们有任何问题或疑问，
you can always visit us at our website EnglishPod.com and we'll be there to answer it.
可以随时访问我们的网站EnglishPod.com，我们会在那里回答。
Bye everyone.
大家再见。
Eoin Le Know at elo titlo.com
Eoin Le Know 在 elo titlo.com